Imagine making plans to
watch a TV programme.
You check the time of your show,
then you wait hours, days or even weeks
because it will be shown exactly once.
That is the way the parents of
today’s teenagers used to watch TV.
Of course, all that changed when
on-demand streaming services appeared.
Today, we don’t even have to wait
for new episodes to be released.
In 2013, Netflix released
all thirteen episodes
of the first season of House of Cards
together.
This decision completely changed
the way we consume content.
Now you come home from school,
and simply download the series
your friends say is a must-see TV show.
Soon, it’s past your bedtime, and
you’ve already watched seven episodes.
Just one more, you promise yourself…
Binge-watching
is the practice of watching many
episodes of a show back-to-back.
It is made easier by the fact that
on-demand streaming services
have hundreds of shows to choose from,
the latest ones and the classic ones.
A survey by Netflix
found that over 70% of people connected
binge-watching with positive feelings.
It helps us connect with other people.
When a large number of people
watch the same show,
they are able to relate with each other
and share what they think about it.
Today, you can discuss a popular show
with your close friend at school
and fans of the show from
another part of the world.
Binge-watching programmes once in a while
can help us reduce stress.
It helps us to relax and stop thinking
about school or problems we may have.
But there are clear disadvantages, too.
Watching TV for hours on end can lead
to physical health problems,
like weight gain,
low energy,
or poor quality of sleep.
Binge-watching can also cause
mental health issues,
such as stress because you feel guilty
that you have wasted time
you could spend doing something
useful or active.
It also causes feelings of sadness
when a show ends,
and anxiety about
what will replace it.
Binge-watching is a form of addiction.
To ensure that we don’t let
binge-watching affect our health,
we can set ourselves a time limit,
stop eating unhealthy snacks
while watching shows,
and make sure that we exercise regularly
and have conversations
about the real world.
With these simple habits,
we can continue enjoying shows
and stay in good physical
and mental health.